Finding Aid for Philip M. Foisie papers, 1930-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip M. Foisie papers 1930-1944 1942-1944
Foisie, Philip M.
0436 Aa 2
The Philip M. Foisie papers include language textbooks, workbooks, and training materials from the Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS) of the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Foisie used the materials between 1943 and 1944 as a student in the Military Intelligence Japanese Language School (MIJLS), part of the AIJLS. The military ran the intensive language center during World War II to gain a stronger understanding of the Japanese language and culture.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in October 2002 (donor no. 9261 ) and in October 2008 through the Center for Japanese Studies (Donor no. 3854).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Philip Manning Foisie (1922-1995), was among the 1944 class of the Military Intelligence Japanese Language School (MIJLS), part of the Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS) of the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. The military-run program trained students in combat techniques, military government work in Japan, and Japanese language and culture.
Foisie served as a military intelligence office in China during World War II. After the war, Foisie remained in Shanghai, working for relief agencies. He became a journalist and worked for national and international newspapers. Joining the Washington Post in 1955 as cable news editor, Foisie became foreign editor and assistant managing editor for foreign news. Leaving the Washington Post, Foisie moved to the International Herald-Tribune as executive editor. He returned to the United States in 1989 to serve as ombudsman for the Stars and Stripes military newspapers published in Europe and Japan.
In 1995, Foisie died of a heart attack.
The collection is organized into two series Textbooks and Student Language Workbooks of the Military Intelligence Japanese Language School (MIJLS), part of the Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS) of the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor.
Subjects:
Japanese language--Conversation and phrase books.; Japanese language--Study and teaching.; United States. Army. Japanese Language School (University of Michigan)
- Student Language Workbooks 1930-1944
  Textbooks series (2 linear feet, 1930-1944) includes course books, reference books, and dictionaries. Introductions to Japanese writing are included in the collection. Reference materials covering military terms, commands, and tactics, will be of interest to researchers. Textbooks of Japanese personal and surnames are of interest to researchers.
  - Vocabulary List: Property of Translation (Box 1)
  - Readings 1944, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Japanese Glossary of Signal Terms (Box 1)
  - Military Language Glossaries 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Geographical Terms (Box 1)
  - Terms of Military Value 1943 (Box 1)
  - Kanji, Book I 1944 (Box 1)
  - Kanji Book II (Box 1)
  - Kanji Book III (Box 1)
  - Kanji Practice (Box 1)
  - Additional Vocabulary Lists 1943 (Box 1)
  - Conversation Vocabulary Lists 1944 (Box 1)
  - Romanji Maki Shi [Romanji Volume 4] (Box 1)
  - Heigo Tokuhon [Military Reading Book] (Box 1)
  - Heigo Tokuhon Two [Military Reading Book, Two] (Box 1)
  - Written Exercises Accompanying Naganuma Book II (Box 1)
- Textbooks 1943-1944
  Student Language Workbooks series (.5 linear feet, 1943-1944) include workbooks, maps, glossaries, vocabulary lists, readings, and practice sheets. The series does include conversational Japanese workbooks, but highlights vocabulary of particular interest to the military and to soldiers. The Heigo Tokuhon [Military Reading Book] and Heigo Tokuhon Two [Military Reading Book Two] will be of interest to researchers.
  - Yamagiwa, Joseph K. Modern Conversational Japanese, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Concordance between Naganuma Book II and Modern Conversational Japanese (Box 1)
  - Concordance between Naganuma Book III and Yamagiwa, Modern Conversational Japanese (Box 1)
  - Yamagiwa, Joseph K. Introduction to Japanese Writing, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Rose-Innes,A. English-Japanese Conversation Dictionary (Box 1)
  - "Bokuseki" [Trees and Stones: A Modern Play] (Box 2)
  - Gillis, I. V. and Pai Ping-ch'i Japanese Surnames, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Gillis, I. V. and Pai Ping-ch'i Japanese Personal Names, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Manual Of Chinese-Manchurian Personal and Place Names, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Exercises, Grammar Notes, and Vocabulary Based on the Naganuma Readers, Book I, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Sanseido's New Concise English-Japanese Dictionary (Box 2)
  - Sanseido's New Concise Japanese-English Dictionary (Box 2)
  - Yoshitaro, Takenobu (General Editor) Kenkyusha's New Japanese-English Dictionary, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Fuzambo's Comprehensive English-Japanese Dictionary 1942 (Box 2)
  - Mathews, R. H. Kuoyü Primer: Progressive Studies in the Chinese National Language, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Creswell, H. T., J. Hiraoka, and R. Namba A Dictionary of Military Terms, English-Japanese, Japanese-English, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Rose-Innes,A. Beginner's Dictionary of Chinese-Japanese Characters and Compounds, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Cursive Character Code [Japanese Language Textbook] (Box 3)
  - Important Military Commands: Passing the General Exam, Vol. 1 [Japanese Language Textbook] (Box 3)
  - Practical Application of Tactics Reference Book [Japanese Language Textbook] (Box 3)
  - Normal Japanese Reader, Volume 2 [Japanese Language Textbook] (Box 3)
  - Ueda's Daijiten [Japanese dictionary of Chinese Characters and compounds] (Box 3)
Related Material
For additional records, the researcher should consult the Grant K. Goodman and Joseph D. Sasaki papers and the Center for Japanese Studies records. Several textbooks and reports about the program authored by Joseph K. Yamagiwa are cataloged separately in the Bentley Library.
The University of Michigan War Historian records also contain further information on the Japanese Language program and the negotiations for hosting the program in Ann Arbor.